Finding Aid for Charles Horton Cooley Papers 1872-1930
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles Horton Cooley papers 1872-1930
Cooley, Charles Horton, 1864-1929.
2 portraits
1 oversize folders
7 linear feet (in 9 boxes)
Professor of sociology at University of Michigan. Papers contain correspondence, including letters, 1881-1884, written to his family while traveling in Europe, and correspondence with his parents, Mary E. and Thomas M. Cooley, and his wife, Elsie Jones Cooley; addresses, notes, essays, book reviews, notes and material for sociology courses; student notebook, 1893-1894, on lectures given by John Dewey; diary of a trip through the Smokey Mountains in 1883; and journals detailing his personal thoughts and tracing the evolution of his ideas on sociology and democracy; and photographs.
851001 Aa 2 Ac
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was formed from a number of accessions received between 1939 and 1979 from Mrs. Arthur Baker (Donor 1225 ), Mary Cooley (Donor 1255 ), and Edward Jandy (Donor 3150 ).
The collection is open for research.
Portions of the Charles Horton Cooley papers have been microfilmed and can be obtained through inter-library loan. The microfilm includes Cooley's journals, correspondence with Thomas M. Cooley, correspondence with his parents, Cooley's notes on philosophy lectures by John Dewey and other selected papers. Microfilmed items are indicated in the contents list.
Charles Horton Cooley was born August 17, 1864 in Ann Arbor, Michigan. He was the son of Michigan Supreme Court Justice Thomas M. Cooley and Mary Horton Cooley. He attended the public schools of Ann Arbor graduating from high school in 1880. He enrolled at the University of Michigan that fall at the age of sixteen but only graduated in 1887 having spent some time in Europe prior to completing his degree requirements. Also during this period, Cooley had worked with the Industrial Works at Bay City as a draftsman, then going to Washington D.C. where he was employed with the Interstate Commerce Commission and the census bureau.
Prior to receiving his doctor of philosophy in 1894, Cooley had become in 1892 an assistant in political economy at the University of Michigan. In 1895, Cooley was instrumental in the establishment of a course of study in sociology. In 1899, he was appointed assistant professor of sociology, then junior professor (1904) and full professor (1907). Cooley was the author of several works, including Human Nature and the Social Order (1902); Social Organization (1909); Social Process (1918); and Life and the Student (1927).
Cooley was widely respected as one of the seminal thinkers in the field of sociology for his thoughts and writings on social theory. In his writings, Cooley elaborated concepts of the individual and society. The central principal in Cooley's sociological view was that the essential facts of social life are mental, and the conduct of persons and groups and the forms of institutions, are the result of fundamental mental phenomena.
Cooley died May 7, 1929.
The Charles Horton Cooley papers consist of correspondence, journals, Cooley's notes for lectures, student notebooks, various writings by Cooley, articles about Cooley and reviews of his books and photographs. The papers, particularly the correspondence, reveal much about Cooley's personal and family life. The journals and lecture notes provide insight into the development of Cooley's ideas and his place in the field of sociology. Though the collection includes only a small amount of correspondence with other leading sociologists, the journals and lecture notes record Cooley's comments on and critiques of the theories and methods in the developing discipline.
Subjects:
Cooley, Charles Horton, 1864-1929.; Cooley family.; Sociology.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Philosophy.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Sociology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Student notebooks.; Dewey, John, 1859-1952.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Ann Arbor High School (Mich.). Class of 1912.; Boats.; Camping.; Children.; Cooley, Charles Horton, 1864-1929.; Cooley family.; Cooley, Mary Horton, 1830-1890.; Cooley, Thomas McIntyre, 1824-1898.; Photographs.; Prints.; Samovar Club (University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Literary clubs.; Women.; World War, 1914-1918--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; World War, 1914-1918--Education and the war.; Nast, Thomas, 1840-1902.; H.B. Hall & Sons.; E.G. Williams & Bro.
Contributors:
Angell, Robert Cooley, 1899-1984; Bain, Read, 1892-; Bernard, L. L. (Luther Lee), 1881-1951.; Blanshard, Paul, 1892-1980; Cooley, Thomas McIntyre, 1824-1898.; Giddings, Franklin Henry, 1855-1931.; Holt, Henry, 1840-1926.; Lane, Victor Hugo, 1852-1930.; Pond, Allen Bartlit, 1858-1929.; Ross, Edward Alsworth, 1866-1951.; Small, Albion Woodbury, 1854-1926.; Sorokin, Pitirim Aleksandrovich, 1889-1968.; Taylor, Graham, 1851-1938.; Thomas, Calvin, 1854-1919.; Tufts, James Hayden, 1862-1942.; Ward, Lester Frank, 1841-1913.; Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Correspondence
  The correspondence is largely with family members, much of it with Elsie Jones, his fiancée and wife. There is only a limited amount of correspondence with professional colleagues. These include Franklin H. Giddings, Henry Holt, Edward A. Ross, Albion W. Small, Pitirim A. Sorokin, Calvin Thomas, James H. Tufts, Lester Ward, and Booker T. Washington. A selective index to correspondents is attached to this finding aid.
  - General 1894-1929
    - Undated (Box 1)
      (microfilm copy available, mf621)
    - 1894-1928 (Box 1)
    - 1927-1929 (1977 Accession)
      - A-BI (Box 1)
      - CC-K (Box 1)
      - L-P (Box 1)
      - Q-Z (Box 1)
      - Alfred A. Knopf (largely concerning Life and The Student) (Box 1)
    - 1928-1929 (1977 accession) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with his parents, Thomas M. and Mary Horton Cooley
    - 1872-1881 (Box 1)
      (microfilm copy available, mf620-mf621)
    - January-May 1882 (Box 1)
    - June-December 1882 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1883 (Box 1)
    - July-December 1883 (Box 1)
    - January-March 1884 (Box 1)
    - April-June 1884 (Box 1)
    - July-December 1884 (Box 1)
    - 1885-1888 (Box 1)
    - 1889-1895 (Box 1)
    - 1882-1884 from mother (1997 accession; not microfilmed) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Elsie Jones
    - July-October 1888 (Box 1)
    - November 1888 (Box 1)
    - December 1888 (Box 1)
    - January 1889 (Box 1)
    - February 1889, March 1889 (Box 1)
    - April 1889 (Box 1)
    - May 1889 (Box 1)
    - August-September 1889 (Box 1)
    - October 1889 (Box 1)
    - November 1889 (Box 1)
    - December 1889 (Box 1)
    - January 1890 (Box 1)
    - February 1890 (Box 1)
    - March 1890 (Box 1)
    - April 1890 (Box 1)
    - May 1890 (Box 2)
    - June 1890 (Box 2)
    - July 1890 (Box 2)
    - October-November 1890 (Box 2)
    - December 1890 (Box 2)
    - 1891 (Box 2)
    - 1892-1894 (Box 2)
    - 1896-1899 (Box 2)
    - 1900-1909 (Box 2)
    - 1910 (Box 2)
    - 1911 (Box 2)
    - 1912-1913, 1914 (Box 2)
    - 1917-1925 (Box 2)
    - 1926, 1928 [1979 accession] (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Letters of condolence 1929 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence of Elsie Jones Cooley 1939 (Box 2)
    - Letters from Mary Cooley to Elsie Jones 1888-1890 (Box 2)
    - Letter from Thomas M. Cooley to Elsie Jones March 1890 (Box 2)
    - Note from James B. Angell to Elsie Cooley and Mary Cooley (sister of Charles) 1907 (Box 2)
- Journals/Diaries, 1882-1929
  The journals, which Cooley kept through most of his life, include brief observations on daily events and activities as well as more extended entries on his reading, research, and sociological and philosophical subjects. Also included is a diary of a trip Cooley made through the Great Smoky Mountains in 1883.
  - Index to journals prepared by Professor Glenn Jacobs 1979 (Box 2)
  - Undated (Box 2)
  - 1882 (Box 2)
    (microfilm copy available, mf617)
  - 1882, journal of trip to Colorado (Box 2)
  - August-October 1883, diary of trip through the Great Smokey Mountains (Box 2)
  - February-April 1984, diary written while in Munich (Box 2)
  - 1887-1888 (Box 2)
  - 1889-1891 (Box 2)
  - No. 6: May 2-July 6, 1890 (Box 2)
    (microfilm copy available, mf616)
  - No. 10: July 21, 1895-April 26, 1896 (Box 2)
  - No. 11: May 7, 1896-March 21, 1897 (Box 2)
  - No. 12: May 2, 1897-August 7, 1898 (Box 2)
  - No. 13: August 8, 1898-1899 (Box 3)
  - No. 14: 1900-December 20, 1901 (Box 3)
  - No. 15: December 24, 1901-September 12, 1902 (Box 3)
  - No. 16: September 19, 1902-June 25, 1903 (Box 3)
  - No. 17: July 8, 1903-August 28, 1904 (Box 3)
  - No. 18a: September 9, 1904-February 6, 1908 (Box 3)
  - No. 18b: February 16, 1908-January 1, 1910 (Box 3)
  - No. 19: February 6 1910-October 1911 (Box 3)
  - No. 20: October 30, 1911-September 7, 1913 (Box 3)
  - No. 21: November 1913-April 11, 1919 (Box 3)
  - No. 22: April 20, 1919-June 5, 1925 (Box 3)
  - No. 23: June 6, 1925-November 4, 1928 (Box 3)
  - No. 24: October 4, 1928-April 7, 1929 (Box 3)
- Course Materials
  The course materials series includes Cooley's notes (1894) on lectures of John Dewey. There is also a "published" set of notes for Cooley's Principles of Sociology course as well as his notes for the first sociology course at the university taught by Cooley in 1894-95. With this series, there are the notes taken by an unidentified University of Michigan student of courses taken in 1902 with several of the university's better known professors. It is unclear how Cooley came into possession of the notebooks.
  - Student notebook: philosophy lectures of John Dewey 1894 (Box 4)
    (includes several lectures on anthropological ethics and lectures on political philosophy)
    (microfilm copy available, mf619)
  - Principles of Sociology undated (For Edwards Brothers publishers), 2 volumes (Box 4)
  - Sociology course 1894 (Box 4)
    Note by Cooley indicates these are likely his notes for the first sociology course taught at Michigan
  - Sociology course 1894-1895 (Box 4)
  - Student Notes (Notes of unknown University of Michigan student)
    - Sociology lectures of Charles H. Cooley 1902 (Box 4)
    - History lectures of Andrew C. McLaughlin 1902 (Box 4)
    - French lectures of John R. Effinger 1902 (Box 4)
    - German lectures of Jonathan A.C. Hildner 1902 (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous: Writings, Notes, and Personal
  The Miscellaneous (Writings, Notes, and Personal) series consists of drafts of various writings, reprints of articles, reviews of his works, biographical and genealogical information.
  - Drafts of various writings and collected material 1894, 1924, undated, 3 volumes (Box 4)
  - Elsie Jones Cooley papers concerning trip to Europe 1891-1892, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Reviews and related
    - Human Nature and the Social Order 1902-1903 (Box 5)
    - Social Organization 1909-1915 (Box 5)
    - Social Process 1918-1919 (Box 5)
    - Life and the Student 1927-1928 (Box 5)
  - Notes and other materials from the time when he was a student in Munich 1884 (Box 5)
  - Essay presented to American Seminary 1885 (Box 5)
  - Notes made at Concord, Massachusetts 1891 (Box 5)
  - Articles undated (Box 5)
  - Lecture Notes undated (Box 5)
  - Reprints of articles (Box 5)
  - Articles concerning Cooley 1909-1923, undated (Box 5)
  - Genealogical papers 1901-1939 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous subjects undated (Box 5)
  - Concerning the development of sociology at the University of Michigan (Box 5)
  - Miscellanea (includes correspondence, notes, remembrances of Cooley by Jacob Billikopf, and marriage certificate) (Box 5)
  - "Charles Horton Cooley: A Memorial Read before the Senate of the University of Michigan, April 10, 1930" (Box 5)
  - Passport 1883 (Folder 1)
  - Diploma 1884
  - Sketch of boat undated
- Photographs
  The Cooley papers contain a small number of photographs and prints including portraits Charles and his parents, and photos of family and friends and colleagues.
  - Cooley, Charles Horton, portraits (Box 5)
  - Cooley, Mary Horton
    - Portraits (Box 5)
    - Framed portrait (frame size 53x45 cm.) (Object 1)
      (in vault)
  - Cooley, Thomas McIntyre
    - Portraits (Box 5)
    - Framed portrait (frame size 53x45 cm) (Object 2)
  - Cooley family, friends, and colleagues (including Ann Arbor High School Class of 1912) (Box 5)
  - World War I, University of Michigan students being sworn into Navy (Box 5)
  - Photo Album (includes camping and boating scenes) (Box 5)
  - Samovar Club (Folder 1)
- Prints
  - Thomas McIntyre Cooley portraits (Box 5)
    Engravings by E.G. Williams & Bro. and H.B.Hall & Sons
  - Thomas McIntyre Cooley portrait (Folder 1)
    Print by Thomas Nast, Jr.
- Research Notes used in the preparation of lectures, books and articles
  The research notes series consists of handwritten and typed notes on 5x6 (for the most part) slips of paper grouped together in small packets. Some are labeled and appear to be notes for specific projects or courses. Others seem to be topical notes on Cooley's reading and research. The notes were found in Cooley's desk following his death. Whatever order and arrangement Cooley had maintained has likely been lost in the transfer and boxing of the notes. The packets which could be readily identified are listed in the contents list.
  - Anthropology (Box 6)
  - Art (Box 6)
  - Art Spirit (Box 6)
  - Biology and Sociology (Box 6)
  - Botanical notes (Box 6)
  - Caste (Box 6)
  - Child study -- Joan (Box 6)
  - Child study -- Mary Elizabeth (Box 6)
  - Children (Box 6)
  - Church (Box 6)
  - Cities, tenements (Box 6)
  - Class (Box 6)
  - Communication (Box 6)
  - Conflict (Box 6)
  - Crime (Box 6)
  - Culture (Box 6)
  - Degeneration; particularism; other topics (Box 6)
  - Dissipation (Box 6)
  - Dissipation, recreation (Box 6)
  - Education (Box 6)
  - Education, philanthropy, etc (Box 6)
  - Elementary social relations (Box 6)
  - Family (Box 7)
  - Foreign element (Box 7)
  - Greater life (Box 7)
  - Group (Box 7)
  - Industry (Box 7)
  - Instinct (Society and the Individual) (Box 7)
  - Institutions (Box 7)
  - Institutions and the individual (Box 7)
  - James (William) others, notes on (Box 7)
  - Lecture material (Box 7)
  - Lectures (Box 7)
  - Life and the Student chapter notes
    - Art, Science and Sociology (Box 7)
    - Control (Box 7)
    - Human Nature (Box 7)
    - Larger life (Box 7)
    - "Our Times" (Box 7)
    - Progress (Box 7)
    - Reading and Writing (Box 7)
    - Thinking (Box 7)
    - Teacher (Box 7)
    - Understanding Perception (Box 7)
  - Meditations (Box 7)
  - Method (Box 7)
  - Method, Research, etc. (Box 7)
  - Method notes: Arts and Sciences (Box 7)
  - Nationality (Box 7)
  - Opportunity and education (Box 7)
  - Organization, general view of (Box 7)
  - Prestige, conduct, degeneration (Box 7)
  - Process, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Race (Box 7)
  - Relief (charity) (Box 7)
  - Selection, Control, Standards (Box 8)
  - Self and the World (Box 8)
  - Sentiment (Box 8)
  - Sentiment, Motive, etc. (Box 8)
  - Settlements (Box 8)
  - Social feeling (Box 8)
  - Social Mind (Box 8)
  - Social Process -- Technique of Rural Sociology (Box 8)
  - Social Self-Feeling (Box 8)
  - Social Will (Box 8)
  - Socialism (Box 8)
  - Sociology Dept. (University of Michigan), notes (Box 8)
  - Sociology notes (Box 8)
  - State (Box 8)
  - Success (Box 8)
  - Suicide (Box 8)
  - Thinking; Teaching (Box 8)
  - Trends (Box 8)
  - Variation (Box 8)
  - Writing, Art of (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, unidentified, fragment, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 23 folders (Box 9)
Selective Index to Chronological Correspondence, 1894-1928
Giddings, Franklin Henry, 1855-1931
Oct. 27,1902
Holt, Henry, 1840-1926.
June 26,1899
Ross, Edward Alsworth, 1866-1951.
Nov. 2,1894
Small, Albion Woodbury, 1854-1926.
Dec. 2, 1902
Sorokin, Pitrim Alexandrovich, 1889-1968.
Sept. 16, 1927
Thomas, Calvin, 1854-1919.
May 28, 1903
Tufts, James Hayden, 1862-1942.
May 2, 1903; Jan. 13, 1910
Ward, Lester Frank, 1841-1913
1898; 1900; 1902; 1907 [Attached to letter from B. Stern to E.C. Jandy, Nov. 19,19311
Washington, Booker Taliaferro, 1856-1915.
Dec. 27, 1909
Selective Index of Alphabetical Correspondence, 1927-1929
Angell, Robert Cooley, 1899-
Oct. 5, 1928; Oct. 8, 1928; Dec. 3, 1928; Feb. 2, 1929
Bain, Read, 1892-
Sept. 5, 1927; Sept. 11, 1927; Sept. 27, 1927; Oct. 2, 1927; Aug. 21, 1927; Dec. 10, 1927; Dec. 18, 1927
Bernard, Luther Lee, 1881-1951
Jan. 8, 1927; Feb. 14, 1927; Mar. 28, 1927; Apr. 1927; Aug. 11, 1927; Aug. 15, 1927; Aug. 24, 1927; Sept. 30, 1927; Jan. 31, 1928; Feb. 6, 1928; Feb. 27, 1928; Mar. 25, 1928
Pond, Allen Bartlit, 1858-1929.
Sept. 30, 1927; Feb. 2, 1929; Feb. 4, 1929; Feb. 13, 1929
Sorokin, Pitrim Alexandrovich, 1889-1968.
Apr. 20, 1928; Apr. 23, 1928
Taylor, Graham, 1851-1938.
Jan. 5, 1928; Jan. 15, 1928; Jan. 20, 1928
Wenley, Robert Mark, 1861-1929.
Nov. 23, 1927